that out so we're going to have our our
questions now and we're going to do it
the way we we did it last week we'll go
from one side to the other there is one
person that we're going to recognize
right off the bat I don't know who that
is but John does she spoke to me in yes
okay so we'll start there and we'll go
on thank you would you mind speaking to
the how this relates to our attitudes
with regards to climate change please
thank you what I really wanted to
address this because I I want to answer
this question somewhat at length okay so
this would be a long answer so a
colleague and supporter of mine Thomas
Bjorkman talks about what he calls the
meta-crisis see it's getting even darker
and he talks about that you know of
course includes climate change and it
includes growing socio-economic
disparity and the social stressors that
that is causing we don't it's not in the
news right now but the energy crisis is
going to return inevitably and what do
you and we are also facing at the same
time for some reasons you might have
seen or at least can divine from what I
said we're facing progressive senses of
alienation and disenfranchisement from
public institutions people are losing
faith in the institutions and the
institutions are responding with
stagnation and gridlock so all of these
factors are not independent that's why
he calls it a meta crisis they're all
mutually reinforcing each other the meta
crisis
now here's the thing that I want to say
about what I was talking about
let's take climate change as it clearly
right it's exactly trying to deal with
it is exacerbated by these these these
issues of social alienation and
political polarization and stagnation
because we get a lot of disinformation
about it but in terms of the science the
science is in and it's been in for quite
a while and it's convincing right and
the fact that some people are trying to
make us hold this science to standards
that we don't hold medical science to is
ridiculous well you can't prove it yeah
ok I can't really prove the way you're
asking me that this bacteria causes
everybody to have this disease but we
don't require that level of proof
because people are dying from the
disease and the planet is dying from
these issues we know this so the reason
why promise is interested in my work I
believe is because I've proposed that
the meaning crisis and the meta crisis
are interlocking that the meaning crisis
is helping to exacerbate these factors
it's creating a kind of mental fog it's
creating a tendency to reciprocal
narrowing and cognitive inflexibility
like being trapped in the wrong
formulation of the mutilated chessboard
so that we can't break out I think that
and of course there's feedback before I
go into my next point there's feedback
when people look out and see a world
that in many ways they feel is dying
that reinforces the meaning crisis so
they're feeding on each other the mental
fogging right and it's making it harder
and harder for us to get the needed
innovation because we're gonna have to
make fundamental transformations in who
and what we are in order to dress
address the meta-crisis I want to make
that point even more profoundly we need
comprehensive transformation in
cognition consciousness character and
commune
and the only thing that has done that
for us in the past comprehensively have
been religions we tried political
alternatives in the 20th century and
they drenched the world in Titanic and
terrifying amounts of blood so the nuns
and no NES look at that and they say no
no there is no political solution to
quote the police the rock group right
but because of the meeting crisis they
find and this is I need you to hear this
deeply I need you to hear this deeply
they find the existing religions
irrelevant they don't find them faults
the new atheists are dropping in
importance it's not a falsity issue
because way before you make judgments of
truth you have to be bound to something
in relevance they reject these religions
because they find them irrelevant one of
the things I explore them to my series
awakening from the meaning crisis is how
did we get to this place where we are so
so in such a wisdom famine and we are so
disconnected from those sets of
practices that could potentially offer
us the comprehensive transformation we
need I talked about this is the problem
of needing a religion that's not a
religion we need something that is
comprehensive so it needs to be a
religion in that sense but they can't be
any of the established religions and it
can't be the political pseudo religious
ideologies that led to totalitarian
terror so we're locked we're locked and
that's how these people feel they feel
that there's no political solution and
there's no traditional solution there's
no religious solution there's no
political solution so we need a religion
that's not a religion how do we do that
how do we do that and here's the thing
and I was talking to somebody else
during the break and I want to point
something out and it goes towards that
modal confusion we're talking about
there's subjective well-being which is
how well do you feel how good it like
how good is how good are you feeling you
have enough stuff you're feeling good
healthy vital so our culture loves
subjective well-being it pumps us and
pumps more get more get more it tells us
kind of the wrong thing it tells us get
more wealth and power because that will
increase your subjective well-being the
problem with that is the curve looks
like this initially as they get more
wealth and power subjective well-being
goes up really fast and then once I pass
the threshold of plateaus and so it
becomes irrational I have to get huge
differences in wealth to make small
differences in subjective well-being so
we're locked into frustration and
secondly it confuses and conflates modal
confusion subjective well-being with
meaning in life let me give you and I
use this example with the person in the
break let me give you something with
these to come apart having a child when
people have a child all of the measures
of subjective well-being go down their
health goes down their sleeping goes
down their psychological contentedness
goes down they don't like the person
they've previously loved how did you get
me into this right right they doubt they
doubt themselves their wealth goes down
you lose years of life if you have a
child by the way your finances are
hammered so all the things that you're
told
make you lose them all they get hammered
we know this we measure it why do people
do it then they say meaning and life
goes up people will make Titanic
sacrifices to their lifestyle if they
can get more meaning in life but if they
have a famine of meaning in life and
wisdom they will reciprocally narrow
modal confusion and hang on to their
lifestyle and not make the needed
changes that's how I think the meaning
crisis and the meta crisis and
other questions
that's a hard one to follow I wanted to
go back to what you talked about with
addiction yes and the opening and
closing and you you said with video
games which are considered to be an
addiction by many that that flow
increases right the attraction expert
flow is a good thing if you're rock
climbing and so are there qualitative
differences yeah yep the kinds of flow
that's an excellent question so she's
putting her finger on a potentially a
looming contradiction and so I want to
try and alleviate that I've done some
work with Alex funk on this and other
people so the thing about rock climbing
is because you're interacting with the
causal structures of the world it
actually is transferable believe it or
not to the world at large let me give
you my own personal example of this so a
long time ago I started doing Tai Chi
Chuan and Taoism is the religion of flow
that's the Tai Chi is about getting you
into the flow state and for a very long
time I was just doing it and then
something happened people came up to me
because I was in grad school and they
said what's going on and I thought oh no
I've done something wrong and I said
what do you mean and they said you were
you're thinking differently you're
arguing differently you're writing
differently and and it was the Tai Chi
skills were member of being a general
problem solver we're generalizing they
were percolating through my life because
Tai Chi moves my real body in the real
world and gets me to move my attention
in the real environment and that
actually and it gets me to try and
balance and inward and out all of that
stuff so the paradox of flow and video
games is you're getting the reciprocal
opening within a world that is actually
closing you off so there isn't actually
a contradiction so Alex funk talked my
student talks about this he talks about
what you do is you get
local agency enhancement in the game at
the expense of real-world agency and so
well though and and this is what I tried
to show you the very machinery that
makes you adaptive can be hijacked in a
negative way and so the video games are
hijacking the flow and meaning in life
because I try to show you both of that
but they're doing it in such a way that
actually ultimately starves you because
it can't generalize I I'll try to
formulate my question meaningfully the
neurotransmitter analogy with reciprocal
narrowing reciprocal opening and
changing our arena the impact of of
antidepressants our addiction to an
antidepressant society and what's
happening to seniors who are locked in
sometimes all of that is part of my
question in the context of what you've
described yeah no no this like this is a
big thing you guys are all asking
somebody asked me a small question so
again again this is a kind of modal
confusion we're getting locked into a
having mode of dispensing medication and
forgetting about the being mode that is
needed for therapeutic intervention so
the research shows that you need a triad
to deal with to help people you yes you
should use medication but you also need
consistent long term therapeutic
intervention and you also need a
reorganization of the person's social
network you need a much more
comprehensive strategy and we have
tended to go to this poll because it's
easily marketable and it's something you
can
have and take you take your medication
rather than how are you going to undergo
a process of transformation and so the
fact that we are doing that is making a
problematic because what you see
happening in the therapeutic world is
you and it's really interesting I was
again talking to somebody during the
break about this you see people taking
CBT right which is actually derived from
stoicism explicitly as a wisdom
tradition cognitive behavioral therapy
you see them integrating that with
emotion focused therapy right you see
them integrating that with sort of forms
of serious play therapy you see them
then recommending that people take up a
more comprehensive way of life like
stoas what you see is the therapeutic
world is moving towards sort of
organically without realizing it trying
to grow a religion for people but the
problem is the religion is bloody
expensive its elitist in a financial
sense so the growth shows I think a
correct inkling about what is needed but
the way we have set it into sort of a
capitalist market mentality is actually
going to thwart it to deal or what it
needs what we really need to do another
question please
here's an easy question can you come and
the popularity of a Jordan Peterson your
colleague that's not an easy question
okay so haha I know Jordan personally
and I knew Jordan before you became a
God because he kind of is that and I
also know I also knew him in the context
of we shared many students at U of T and
we were in groups together we appeared
at conferences together we spoke
together his first non-political video
that went big was his discussion with me
about meeting in life okay so I've been
intimately involved now Jordan is
inaccessible and here's the thing first
of all I want to say right away this
Jordan is a really complex guy like
trying to comment him is like trying to
comment on like assignment rice or
something there's so many things
happening all at once that it's very
difficult so that's why I'm being very
guarded and like I said I have a
personal relationship to him and I have
to somehow keep that separate from my
professional relationship with him
because I think there's two reasons why
Jordan is famous is that the right
adjective and I think they're they
interconnect but in ways that need to be
more carefully critiqued and understood
one reason is Jordan put his finger on
the meaning crisis I know this because
like I said we talked we've been talking
about meaning in life right the first
big video was the meaning in life video
but he also so he's got one finger on
the meaning crisis and that's why he can
do things like do a series on the Bible
and hundreds of thousands of people will
watch it but he like
and these to reinforce each other he
also put his finger on a lot of the
political anger and frustration in our
culture he put his finger on that and
that's feet I want to be fair to myself
here now I have explicitly said these
things to Jordan so I'm not speaking out
of turn
I am very critical of sort of his
political response I think it
misrepresents the issue in some skewed
ways I'll give you one clear example and
it's the one that made him famous again
please give me some charity here because
I I think Jordan has a lot to say that's
important and I like Jordan but that
whole issue about the pronouns I'm in
their psychology department I have never
met anybody that came to me from their
pronouns that was martyred motivated by
cultural Marxism I don't even know what
that is every time because it's happened
to me repeatedly somebody came to me
they came to me respectfully they were
in pain then they asked for me to do
something that the university is
supposed to help people do which is
experiment with new identity and so I
said yes and I was happy to do so so I
don't know what that was compared to
what I actually encountered in my
teaching so I'm very hesitant about his
political side for political reasons and
for I don't think it was capturing what
I saw at the University of Toronto now
was he treated appropriately when he
began he brought that issue up no he
wasn't he should have been properly
debated I would have loved to have
debated Jordan on this because it would
have been mutually respectful when I
sent my criticisms to him he said that's
great because I presented counter
arguments they tried to silence him and
that was wrong that was wrong they
shouldn't have done that so
this is why this is turning out to be a
hard question I think that Jordan is
important because he brings into
awareness the meaning crisis its
connections to religion and its tortured
connections but important connections to
political frustration and
disenfranchisement and issues about
identity because issues of identity are
also all I would argue ultimately issues
about your existential mode and we I
think we should try and shift language
away from having an identity to becoming
a person that's moral confusion and that
points towards well I think Jordan is
good to put his finger on these things I
have criticisms of it
I think his Jungian approach to try and
understanding the meaning crisis while
valuable is insufficient I also have
criticisms of his interpretation of Jung
he is he's interpreted Jung largely in a
way that is an apologetic for
Christianity traditional theistic
Christianity I think that is a deepness
reading of Jung I have a video that
they're talking to a union
psychotherapist where we discussed that
issue is Jordan right that mythology
matters yes it does but I'm I'm worried
about his use of Jung and I also think
the issue of meaning in life should be
tackled with our comprehensive cognitive
science not just from a Jungian
framework which is what I tried to show
you here today
okay that's my best answer for that very
difficult problem thank you for what
seemed to be to me a postgraduate
lecture in psychology I'm worried now
that I stressed you guys out so go no
don't ever invite him back or at least
put a health warning before it begins my
question has to do with their
neuroimaging of brain function and being
in the flow to me being in the flow
could be something as simple as
looking at a flyer and seeing grapes on
sale for a dollar eighty nine and a
pound or hiking out in a sailboat on the
edge of capsizing and and being you know
sailing across the lake or reading a
book and enjoying the moment so I just
wonder have studies been done to
indicate the when when one might be in
the flow and seems to me that's when one
hobby what in flow has a lot to do with
mean I I didn't hear the last thing you
said oh it seems to me that you know the
studies of what have studies been done
on when people are in flow oh okay great
so I turn to right away from you at just
the wrong moment I apologize for that
first of all I want to say something
about the vogue there's been studies
done on that but that's what was leaping
into my mind and then you did that last
thing at the end which is good too so
this has happened you take articles that
have been rejected by journals you do
new nothing else to the articles but put
in a neuroimaging of a brain you
resubmit
the article and then it gets published
this is happening so is there a vogue
yeah here's the other thing neuroimaging
is important but it is not the trump
card evidence because you have to do a
lot of you this is not a film of your
brain you have to do lots of statistical
processing lots of normalization before
you get the data and secondly science is
not just about improving your technology
you have to increase your theoretical
acuity as you increase your
technological precision and we're coming
to realize this is the work of Michael
Anderson get his book beyond phrenology
because we're coming to realize this
idea of functions
being located in specific parts of the
brain is deeply misleading instead he
proposes what he calls the massive
redeployment hypothesis or the secret
reuse the same brain area actually gets
accepted into many different functions
what's that what's that sup patient
let's talk about it in evolutionary
terms and then we'll go back in
cognitive
my tongue did not originally evolved for
speech although I'm using it to speak
right now
that's why lots of animals have tongues
that don't speak my tongue involved to
detect poison so it has lots of nerve
endings move my food around so it's
highly flexible and be just for creepy
reasons of evolution it's also in my air
passageway so it's perfectly
pre-designed it's what's called a pre
adaptation for speech so my speech organ
doesn't have to be evolved from scratch
does that make sense
that means evolution can go much faster
your brain that's the same thing it
doesn't redesign whole new machines
whenever you're learning something it
takes a machine it's already pre
adaptive and exams it so I take the area
of my brain that's for fine grained
movement with my right hand and I exact
it for fine-grained manipulation of
speech in syntax that's why I gesture
when I speak so the idea that you could
oh well there's where the reasoning is
going on
that's like phrenology the brain is much
more dynamically constantly read it's
like your brain is a machine of machines
that can constantly make itself into a
new kind of machine and so trying to
take pictures of that kind of machine
are very very tricky
no matter how precise your picture is
unless you have an adequate theoretical
model it's going to be deeply misleading
so that's where we sit on that I think
now have we done stuff when people are
in flow yes we have we've also done
stuff when people are in insight and
then I'm going to tell you so I'm gonna
go on under at this because it gets kind
of creepy and terrifying so I've got to
keep continue with my theme of sort of
general cheerfully presenting you darken
for me
so in the flow state it's not what you
might think it's not your whole brain
lights up actually most of your
processing shuts down what I've watched
limitless we only use 10% of our brain
that horrible that's just false okay
that if I could if I could do one
socially good thing here now is the idea
that that's false
okay that's false
no qualification false false false false
okay because a lot of the time your
performance improves by large areas of
your brain shutting off because what's
happening in flow is all of the
extraneous processing is being reduced
it's like a laser so that you get the
focus you need for flow what about
insight so what happens in the insight
and again even left right that's miss
right your left hemisphere is not a
fascist your right hemisphere is not an
artist I'm gonna be talking with you in
a Goa crest about all of this stuff in a
couple weeks on Robo wisdom but anyways
so so here here's a better way of
thinking about it I taught you this your
left hemisphere is really good for
well-defined problems your right
hemisphere is really good for
ill-defined problems it's more like that
okay so the left hemisphere works step
by step with individual detail the right
hemisphere tries to work all at once
right so what happens in insight
processing starts on the left side
because oh this is a familiar problem
I'm covering the chessboard oh crap
and then activity shifts this is what
cuneus and Beeman show it shifts
dramatically to the right hemisphere
because now what you're doing is not
trying to solve the problem you're
trying to open up the gestalt you're
trying to change the problem formulation
and what happens is it goes with you and
then it brings it back
and the problem is reformulated that's
insight there's the Eureka factor is a
book if you want to read about this now
here's where it gets interesting so we
have a technology again we need to get
the theoretical precision we don't quite
know why it works
it's called transcranial direct current
stimulation you basically get two
electrodes attached them to a 9-volt
battery and run a current across it
sounds like voodoo but what it does is
it actually helps the brain shift
patterns of activity again we don't know
how or why it's strange but the result
there's lots of evidence that it does
this so guy by the name of chai and
Snider basically put the electrodes on
in a way that's designed to try and
enhance people shifting getting a shift
from the left to right hemisphere and he
found that that tripled people's ability
to solve insight problems and then they
did something I didn't actually show you
there's called the nine dot problem
which is one of the hardest inside
problems around the statistical solution
rate that spontaneous solution rate the
chance that people solve it
spontaneously without help it's
statistically indistinguishable from
zero people think it's a very easy
problem inside very hard it's it's join
all nine dots with four straight lines
you've probably seen a version of it
does it says testicle solution rate is
zero say we had control he had control
groups for Sherman everything but just
at the point they put this montage on
gave them the $9.00 and this spontaneous
solution rate went to 40% the chances of
that happening by chance are one in a
billion
see this used to be where the state
couldn't go are there one very crude
chemical and torture techniques but
that's that's that's going away because
if we can make something that can make
you insightful we can make you something
that's makes you less insightful make
you more prone to self-deception and
right now we have to do it by wire but
we always figure out how to do things by
what why are wirelessly do you want
governments and corporations to have
that so I've made an argument that we
need to do something we haven't done
before we need to make at public policy
we need to have a cultural thing that
these emergent technologies are
explicitly linked to the project of
making people wiser so that for once we
can generate the wisdom of how to use
the technology and specially link that
use to always making us wiser in the use
of it we can actually do that now we
have that potential so I think we're in
a race I've been approached by the US
government actually the US Army I said
No
I gave a talk on Saturday about the
weird kind of cognition that we you the
scientists on earth use in order to use
the Rovers on Mars and it's really
strange and maybe you'll get to see the
talk and I had somebody she came up to
me and she said oh that was such a good
talk I want to know more about your work
so I could better control drones so this
is a long answer far beyond what you
were asking for but I'm trying to show
you that first of all your point about
it being invoked that's a real issue
secondly we are watching what's
happening in the brain when people are
in insight and because we're actually
getting a good theoretical understanding
with the precision that's actually
putting power in our hands and like all
power it's very dangerous okay so that's
my answer to that question
but I I want to thank you John thank you
for blowing our minds for for bringing
some it for making us feel that we're
not alone in the feelings that we all
have many of us are grandparents
and think about our children and think
about the world that they're moving into
and it's not a it's not a pleasant thing
to ponder but I think if they were
taught the way you taught us today they
might be better able to handle it I hope
so
I think I think that would be our our
wish as Grandparents I want to leave you
with with what has happened today and
the reason that we come here every
Wednesday during our lecture series
we're seniors in pursuit of lifelong
learning
it never stops as long as we allow it to
continue so you have certainly taught us
well today and given us much to think
about and much to look at on YouTube so
get your faces on the screens your past
help anyway it's not going to do it's
not going to damage you
so so John thank you we wish you well in
your studies
thank you very much I had a wonderful
wonderful time thank you so much
[Applause]